Guide to the Catherine Strunk Amatruda Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Catherine Strunk Amatruda papers
1929-1983
MS 1363
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.83
(5 boxes)
The papers consist of writings, research data, correspondence, examination materials, and printed material documenting the professonal career of Catherine S. Amatruda, a pediatrician at Yale University and author of several articles and books. The papers highlight Amatruda's clinical research and writing on the norms for infant development and methods for the developmental diagnosis of infant behavior and her collaborative work with Arnold Gesell.
Amatruda, Catherine Strunk, 1903-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Joseph V. Baldwin, 1983.
Arrangement
Arranged in five series: I. Developmental Diagnosis, 1940-1941. II. Developmental Schedules, 1941. III. Topical Files, 1929-1983. IV. Examination Materials, n.d. V. Printed Materials, 1934-1945.
Scope and Contents
The Catherine Strunk Amatruda Papers consist of correspondence, writings, research data, examination materials, and printed material, which document Catherine Amatruda's professional career as a research pediatrician at Yale University. The papers highlight Amatruda's clinical research and writing on the norms for infant development and methods for the developmental diagnosis of infant behavior and her collaborative work with Arnold Gesell.
The Amatruda Papers are organized in five series. SERIES I,DEVELOPMENTAL DIAGNOSIS, contains annotated drafts of the child development study written by Amatruda and Arnold Gesell. This work is the outgrowth of years of clinical research with infants and young children. Amatruda's annotations are often quite extensive, and reflect substantive changes in the format and content of the volume. Appendices (folder 21) contain a series of charts and tables which outlines much of the experimental work conducted.
SERIES II, DEVELOPMENTAL SCHEDULES, contains the raw data used in the formulation of schedules for Developmental Diagnosis. Portions of the data in these files are unpublished, however. Data recorded in parentheses appear to be that of Amatruda, while Gesell's normative data are recorded without parentheses. Asterisks next to data items indicate representative behavior in children at that particular age level.
SERIES III, TOPICAL FILES, contains annual reports, articles, book reviews, correspondence, lectures, miscellanea, and photographs. Annual reports (folder 40) date from 1929 to 1951 and include summary statements on the yearly work of the Yale University Clinic of Child Development and Child Study Center. These reports contain updates on the progress of literary and research projects for Amatruda, Gesell, and others, as well as evaluations of the ongoing work of the entire institution. Articles (folders 41-43) consist of medical and scientific articles written by Amatruda, Gesell, and others.
Correspondence (folders 45-48) contains a single folder of letters to Amatruda (folder 45). These letters are brief notes of thanks or inquiry and include one from Yale president Charles Seymour, who congratulated Amatruda on her book Developmental Diagnosis. The correspondence of Toby (William T.) Amatruda, Catherine Amatruda's son, is arranged in this series (folder 46). Toby and Joseph V. Baldwin, a long-time colleague of Catherine Amatruda, exchanged letters in 1981-1982. Baldwin responded in great detail to requests for biographical and personal information on Amatruda, and he also contributed manuscript materials to the Amatruda Papers. Among his contributions are letters with Arnold Gesell (folder 47). These letters are routine notes, frequently confirming speaking engagements. Two clippings, however, contain articles about the Yale Child Study Center. Baldwin also included his correspondence on the donation of the Amatruda Papers to Yale University (folder 48).
Other material arranged in this series consists of book reviews of Development Diagnosis and other works by Amatruda (folder 44), lectures delivered at a psychiatry seminar (folder 49), photographs of Amatruda with patients (folder 51), and miscellaneous notes and papers (folder 50).
SERIES IV, EXAMINATION MATERIALS, contains a collection of children's toys, such as rattles, balls, blocks, bells, crayons, cards, rings, and books. Other objects include a bottle with pellets, a spoon, penknife, and paper. These items were used extensively in the course of testing conducted by Amatruda.
SERIES V, PRINTED MATERIAL, contains published works which Amatruda authored or contributed to in her professional career.
Biographical / Historical
Catherine S. Amatruda was born March 4, 1903 in Ithaca, New York. Amatruda held the position of research pediatrician at the Clinic of Child Development at Yale University, and was appointed to the Department of Pediatrics and the Child Study Center at Yale. She collaborated on many books, including Developmental Diagnosis (1941). Amatruda died on September 1, 1949, in New Haven, Connecticut.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Child development -- Testing; Medicine; Pediatrics; Women; Physicians; Amatruda, Catherine Strunk, 1903-; Gesell, Arnold, 1880-1961; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Child Study Center
- Developmental Diagnosis, 1940-1941; Series I; 0.5; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains drafts of chapters and related information for Developmental Diagnosis. Files are arranged in chapter sequence, with miscellaneous chapter drafts organized at the end of the series.
  - Preface, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Introduction, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chapters
    - I. The Development of Behaviour, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - II. The Developmental Examination of Behaviour (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - III. Norms of Development, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - IV. The Conduct of the Examination, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - V. Problems of Differential Diagnosis, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - VI. Amentia and Retardation, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - VII. Amentia of High Grade, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - VIII. Amentia of Low Grade, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - IX. Endocrine Disorders, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - X. Convulsive Disorders, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - XI. The Neurological Diagnosis of Infant Behaviour, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - XII. Cerebral Injury, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - XIII. Special Sensory Handicaps, 1941
      General
      See: box 1, folder 15
    - XIV. Deafness, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - XV. Precocity, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - XVI. Environmental Retardation, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - XVII. Clinical Aspects of Child Adoption, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - XVIII. Diagnosis and Guidance, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - XIX. Developmental Supervision, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Appendices A-D, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Illustrations: memos, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Glossary, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Drafts: chapters, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Developmental Schedules, 1941; Series II; 0.5; (1 box)
  This series contains a group of developmental schedules for infants and pre-school children. Portions of the data were used in Developmental Diagnosis. (See: Series I.)
  These schedules are arranged according to the ages of the children tested, with summary material placed in the first folder and undated material organized at the end of the series.
  Actual names of children have been sanitized in these files. The unsanitized original developmental schedules have been destroyed.
  - Quarterly summaries, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - 4-8 weeks, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - 12-16-20 weeks, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - 24-28-32 weeks, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - 36-40-44 weeks, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - 48-52-56 weeks, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - 15 months, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - 18 months, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - 21 months, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - 24 months, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - 27 months, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - 30 months, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - 36 months, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 2, Folder 38-39)
- Topical Files, 1929-1983; Series III; 0.5; (1 box)
  This series contains files arranged alphabetically by the type of material.
  - Annual reports, 1929-1951 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Articles
    - Amatruda, Catherine S., 1936-1951 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Gesell, Arnold, 1932-1943 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Others, 1932-1943 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Book reviews, 1941-1943 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1941-1950, undated (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Amatruda, Toby (William T.), 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Gesell, Arnold, 1944-1978, undated (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Yale University, 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Lectures, undated (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Miscellanea, 1944, 1952, undated (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 51)
- Examination Materials, undated; Series IV; 1.17; (1 box)
  This series consists of the materials used in child development tests. These toys, games, and miscellanea are arranged in a single box.
  - Child testing materials, undated (Box 4)
- Printed Materials, 1934-1945; Series V; 0.5; (1 box)
  This series contains printed material arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Biographies of Child Development, 1939 (Box 5)
  - Developmental Diagnosis, 1941 (Box 5)
  - The Embryology of Behaviour, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - History of Special Education for Mentally Deficient Children in Connecticut, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Infant Behaviour, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 55)